<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Mythoard on GM Sanctuary</title>
    <link>https://diceblog.greylurk.com/tags/mythoard/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in Mythoard on GM Sanctuary</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; 2017. All Rights Reserved</copyright>
    <atom:link href="https://diceblog.greylurk.com/tags/mythoard/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Mythoard 23</title>
      <link>https://diceblog.greylurk.com/post/mythoard-23/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Feb 2017 17:16:40 -0600</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://diceblog.greylurk.com/post/mythoard-23/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;For those who aren&amp;rsquo;t familiar, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.mythoard.com/&#34;&gt;Mythoard&lt;/a&gt; is a monthly subscription box of RPG
goodies that started almost 2 years ago now, and has had a lot of fantastic
books and materials.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I just got my shipment of Mythoard 23, and found some delightful bits.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;creature-components-volume-1-1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.drivethrurpg.com/product/194503/Creature-Components-Vol-1?affiliate_id=6913&#34;&gt;Creature Components: Volume 1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first book that caught my attention was the Creature Components: Volume 1.
Material Components have always been a fascinating feature of D&amp;amp;D. The
common fantasy trope of that &amp;ldquo;one special component&amp;rdquo; that is needed to make a
spell effective is such a powerful thread, but the way it&amp;rsquo;s implemented in D&amp;amp;D
and it&amp;rsquo;s descendents is frequently pretty booring. Either the DM ignores it, or
the game provides &amp;ldquo;Component Pouches&amp;rdquo;, or the like, and it just never gets the
attention it deserves. Creature Components though, takes an interesting approach
to the problem by providing a list of creatures from the Pathfinder bestiary
and ideas on how to use parts of them as &amp;ldquo;supplementary&amp;rdquo; components that can
do things like increase the range, or caster level, or simply add some additional
effects to the spell. Now, this creates a list of min/max options that I&amp;rsquo;m leery
to hand over to players, &amp;ldquo;Oh, we&amp;rsquo;re doing a water adventure, and I&amp;rsquo;m a fire
caster? I&amp;rsquo;m going to go stock up on Dragon Turtle breath glands!&amp;ldquo;. The first
chapter of the book has several fantastic hints on how to introduce harvested
components to your group without worrying too much about profit-minded
murderhobos flooding the economy with owlbear gizzards.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;ponyfinder-ghost-of-the-pirate-queen-2&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.drivethrurpg.com/product/177069/Ponyfinder--Ghost-of-the-Pirate-Queen?affiliate_id=6913&#34;&gt;Ponyfinder - Ghost of the Pirate Queen&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m not a &amp;ldquo;brony&amp;rdquo;, but i&amp;rsquo;ve followed the development of Ponyfinder and
Ponyfinder: 5th age with a bit of bemusement. A lot of my ideas on what
roleplaying and fantasy should be like are based on the cartoons I watched as a
kid, so I think it&amp;rsquo;s good that someone is keeping the tradition alive. A
previous Mythoard netted me a few of &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.playgroundadventures.net/&#34;&gt;Playground Adventures&lt;/a&gt;&amp;rsquo;s other adventures
but this is the first Ponyfinder one, and I continue to be impressed with their
delivery of games using the Pathfinder rules (I believe they also do 5e versions
now as well) aimed specifically at children. Ghost of the Pirate Queen has a few
decidedly childish aspects (Some very simple, but informatitve riddles, a puzzle
that won&amp;rsquo;t challenge most folks past Jr. High, etc), but it&amp;rsquo;s well written, and
has a few interesting plot twists. There&amp;rsquo;s plenty of stuff for adults to enjoy in
this adventure as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the aspects of the module that I like a lot is that each encounter has
ways to resolve the encounter through diplomacy and/or trickery, and it&amp;rsquo;s
explicitly stated that the DM should give equal XP regardless of whether the
enemies are defeated through brawn, diplomacy, or trickery. This keeps the
childlike atmosphere around the game, and definitely fits with the nonviolent
themes of the My Little Pony Tv show. All in all, while it&amp;rsquo;s clearly intended
as an adventure for younger kids (6 and up?), it could be a good time for some
adults approaching it with an open mind.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-traveller-logbook-4&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.rpgnow.com/product/88098/JG-TravellerTraveller-Logbook?affiliate_id=6931&#34;&gt;The Traveller Logbook&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mythoard appears to have come across a big collection of old printed Judges
Guild stuff, and this is a fun little treasure. This is a 64 page booklet
is largely composed of blank character sheets, and blank ship record sheets
for the old GDW version of Traveller.  It&amp;rsquo;s a fun throwback to when we
couldn&amp;rsquo;t just go find a PDF on the game publisher&amp;rsquo;s site, and run it off on
our laser printer. Also, the first dozen or so pages are a repeat of the
character generation tables in the book. It&amp;rsquo;s always nice to have an extra copy
of that at the table.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;traveller-referee-screen-5&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.rpgnow.com/product/88099/JG-Traveller-Referee-Screen?affiliate_id=8931&#34;&gt;Traveller Referee Screen&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another of the old Judge&amp;rsquo;s Guild prints, this is a bright green folded DM screen,
with player stats on one side, and DM relevant info on the other.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-horrid-echoes-of-the-blue-blade&#34;&gt;The Horrid Echoes of the Blue Blade&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This mini-adventure doubles as the checklist for this hoard.  It&amp;rsquo;s a fun little haunted house (inn?)
adventure built for characters of 1-3 level. It&amp;rsquo;s probably most compatible with Pathfinder, but
converting it to any D&amp;amp;D variant would probably take all of about 10 mninutes. This is from the folks at
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.drinkspinrun.com/&#34;&gt;Drink, Spin, Run&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;adventure-hook-card-4&#34;&gt;Adventure Hook Card #4&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the 4th in a set of Mythoard exclusive items.  This is basically just a very short, small adventure hook, and locale. It&amp;rsquo;s a small card you can slip into your dice-box so when the PCs take an unexpected
left turn at the fork in the road, they can make their way to something interesting.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>